<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>berkant gültekin</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/en/</link>
    <description>Recent content on berkant gültekin</description>
    <image>
      <title>berkant gültekin</title>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.151.0</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2025 01:14:44 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Image, Interpretation, and Interface</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/death-of-the-author/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2025 01:14:44 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/death-of-the-author/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;visual-knowledge-and-cultural-bias&#34;&gt;Visual Knowledge and Cultural Bias&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visual forms are never neutral. Every diagram, chart, or image carries &lt;strong&gt;cultural assumptions&lt;/strong&gt; about what knowledge is and how it should look. From geometry to Google Maps, people have used images not just to show information but to &lt;strong&gt;organize and control knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must study images as &lt;strong&gt;interpretive systems&lt;/strong&gt;, not as transparent mirrors of truth. Visual knowledge is &lt;em&gt;constructed&lt;/em&gt; — shaped by values, technologies, and worldviews.
She calls for a &lt;strong&gt;humanistic approach&lt;/strong&gt; to visualization: one that recognizes meaning as &lt;em&gt;situated and subjective&lt;/em&gt;, not universal or purely mathematical.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="visual-knowledge-and-cultural-bias">Visual Knowledge and Cultural Bias</h2>
<p>Visual forms are never neutral. Every diagram, chart, or image carries <strong>cultural assumptions</strong> about what knowledge is and how it should look. From geometry to Google Maps, people have used images not just to show information but to <strong>organize and control knowledge</strong>.</p>
<p>We must study images as <strong>interpretive systems</strong>, not as transparent mirrors of truth. Visual knowledge is <em>constructed</em> — shaped by values, technologies, and worldviews.
She calls for a <strong>humanistic approach</strong> to visualization: one that recognizes meaning as <em>situated and subjective</em>, not universal or purely mathematical.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Every visualization is an argument, not a window on reality.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>
<p><img alt="Renaissance perspective made the viewer the center of space — a model of human dominance." loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/misketmuskat/berkantgultekin/refs/heads/main/static/images/Piero_della_Francesca-Ideal_City-1-1024x295.jpg"></p>
<ul>
<li>Renaissance perspective made the viewer the center of space — a model of human dominance.</li>
<li>Modern data graphics suggest objectivity, but they rely on design choices, color scales, and framing.</li>
<li>Maps and charts hide the politics of what they exclude.</li>
</ul>
<p>Thus, <strong>seeing is not neutral</strong>; it is a cultural act shaped by power, language, and ideology.</p>
<h2 id="the-language-of-graphics-searching-for-rules">The Language of Graphics: Searching for Rules</h2>
<p>Throughout history, scholars have tried to find a <strong>universal grammar of visual communication</strong> — a way to make images function like language, with rules and syntax.</p>
<p>Philosophers and artists from the Renaissance to the Bauhaus believed that visual forms could express truth mathematically. Geometry and proportion were seen as bridges between art and science. Perspective drawings, color wheels, and design grids were all efforts to rationalize vision.</p>
<p>In the 20th century, this search continued in new forms. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wassily_Kandinsky">Wassily Kandisnky</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Klee">Paul Klee</a> at the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bauhaus">Bauhaus</a> studied how shapes and colors evoke emotional and psychological effects. For them, visual form had a kind of <em>spiritual grammar</em>.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_de_Saussure">Ferdinand de Saussure</a> and later <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semiotics">semioticians</a> inspired the idea that visual elements could act as <em>signs</em>, just like words. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacques_Bertin">Jocques Bertin</a>&rsquo;s &ldquo;Semiology of Graphics (1967) proposed a systematic visual language for data: position, size, color, and shape as &ldquo;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visual_variable">visual variables</a>.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Be aware: Such systems treat images as if they have <em>fixed meanings</em>. In reality, interpretation depends on <strong>context</strong> and <strong>culture</strong>. Indeed. A color may signal &ldquo;danger&rdquo; in one society and &ldquo;good luck&rdquo; in another. A map projection can distort the world to favor one region over another.</p>
<p>So while the &ldquo;grammar of graphics&rdquo; is useful for design and analysis, it must be understood as <strong>a rhetoric, not a code</strong> — a way of persuasion, not an absolute truth.</p>
<h2 id="knowledge-and-vision-seeing-as-understanding">Knowledge and Vision: Seeing as Understanding</h2>
<p>Western culture has long linked <strong>vision</strong> with <strong>knowledge</strong> — &ldquo;seeing is believing&rdquo;. From Plato&rsquo;s cave to Enlightenment science, truth has often been imagined as something we see <em>clearly</em>.</p>
<h3 id="historical-roots-of-visual-knowledge">Historical Roots of Visual Knowledge</h3>
<p>In <strong>classical philosophy</strong>, geometry was the highest form of knowledge because it expressed eternal forms through sight and logic. <strong>Renaissance artists</strong> like Alberti and Leonardo turned this idea into practice through linear perspective — a system that placed the human observer at the center of a rational, measurable world. <strong>Modern science</strong> inherited this model: instruments like the telescope or microscope extend human sight, promising objective truth.</p>
<p>This tradition also encodes <em>hierarchies</em> and prioritizes <strong>the eye as an instrument of power</strong>. To &ldquo;see&rdquo; becomes to &ldquo;know&rdquo;, and to know becomes to &ldquo;<strong>control</strong>&rdquo;. Visual systems — maps, anatomical drawings, colonial surveys — have historically served authority, not neutrality. What is visible (and what is left invisible) is a political choice.</p>
<p><strong>Further Reading</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.essentialvermeer.com/technique/perspective/history.html">The History of Perspective — Essential Vermeer</a></li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="note"><p>This is a note.</p></blockquote>
<blockquote class="warning"><p>This is a warning.</p></blockquote>
<blockquote class="danger"><p>This is dangerous.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>bio</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/pp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;berkant gültekin&#34; 
     style=&#34;border-radius: 50%; float: right; margin-left: 20px; width: 280px; height: 280px;&#34; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi. I am Berkant. I’m a Master’s student in Data &amp;amp; Discourse Studies at TU Darmstadt, originally from Turkey. I have passion about understanding complex subjects and identifying connections, particularly within the fields of political theory, sociology, anthropology and language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog is my medium to share insights, thought processes and ideas related to these fields. It is also a space for experimenting with writing, where I keep my writing practice alive.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="/images/pp.jpg" alt="berkant gültekin" 
     style="border-radius: 50%; float: right; margin-left: 20px; width: 280px; height: 280px;" />

<p>Hi. I am Berkant. I’m a Master’s student in Data &amp; Discourse Studies at TU Darmstadt, originally from Turkey. I have passion about understanding complex subjects and identifying connections, particularly within the fields of political theory, sociology, anthropology and language.</p>
<p>This blog is my medium to share insights, thought processes and ideas related to these fields. It is also a space for experimenting with writing, where I keep my writing practice alive.</p>
<p>You can find me at:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/berkantgultekin/">linkedin</a></li>
<li><a href="https://cv.berkantgultekin.com">curriculum vitae</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Enjoy your stay here.</p>
<hr>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>terms and policies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/terms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/terms/</guid>
      <description>Learn more about our terms and policies, including text and code licenses. Your privacy is a priority for us, and you can browse our site with peace of mind that we do not save cookies on your browser.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is my personal blog, the content here is written and edited by me (Berkant Gültekin). By continue to use this website, in any and all forms, constitutes acceptance of these terms and policies.</p>
<p>The content provided is for informational purposes. The posts and projects are my own and may not represent the position, strategy, or opinion of my current or past employers. I will not be liable for any errors or omissions in this information nor for the availability of this information. I will not be liable for any losses, injuries, or damages from the display or use of this information.</p>
<h2 id="privacy-policy">Privacy policy</h2>
<h3 id="cookies-and-tracking">Cookies and Tracking</h3>
<p>This website doesn&rsquo;t use cookies to track or identify users, but it does use Google Analytics to track user engagement and use of the website. The report provided by Google Analytics doesn&rsquo;t have any identifying information on visitors. Please read more about <a href="https://policies.google.com/privacy">Google&rsquo;s Privacy Policy</a>.</p>
<h2 id="license">License</h2>
<p>All source code on this website is licensed under MIT.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-txt" data-lang="txt"><span class="line"><span class="cl">MIT License
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">Copyright 2021-2024 Jaqueline Souza Medeiros
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy of this 
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">software and associated documentation files (the &#34;Software&#34;), to deal in the Software
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">without restriction, including without limitation the rights to use, copy, modify, 
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software, and to 
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following 
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">conditions:
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all copies 
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">or substantial portions of the Software.
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED &#34;AS IS&#34;, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, 
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR 
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE 
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR 
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">OTHER DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">CC-BY-SA-4.0</a> applies for all content otherwise noticed under /post/ and /projects/.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
